<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
    <feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
        <title>Front-end Developer ~ Mat Hayward</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <icon>
           http://mathayward.com/static/images/icons/favicon.png
        </icon>
        <updated>2013-09-19T18:07:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://mathayward.com/feed.xml</id>
        <link type="text/html" href="http://mathayward.com" rel="alternate"/>
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>Jekyll search with JSON</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/search.jpg" alt="Jekyll search with JSON" />
                    <p>You may or may not know that this site is built using <a href="http://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a>, a static site generator. That means there&#39;s no database, so page load speed is much faster.</p>

<p>Without a database though, there&#39;s nothing to query when needed, i.e. when wanting a <a href="/search">search function</a>, so I went about building a work around.</p>

<p>With the <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/docs/templates/">Liquid templating</a> language, used by Jekyll, I built a <a href="/feeds/feed.json">JSON encoded feed</a> for posts and pages on the site which I wanted to show up in search results.</p>

<pre><code>[
    {
        "title": "{{post.title}}",
        "content": "{{post.content | markdownify | strip_html"}}",
        "link": "{{site.url}}{{post.url}}",
        "date": "{{post.date}}",
        "excerpt": "{{post.snippet}}"
    }
    ...
]</code></pre>

<p>I then wrote a Javascript plugin which receives a search term, either from a querystring or a form submission, and looks for the term within the JSON feed.</p>

<p>With this data, it&#39;s pretty simple to output the results directly into the DOM using a template partial.</p>

<figure class="media">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/jekyll-search.png" alt="Jekyll search" class="media__item">
</figure>

<p>That&#39;s it explained in it&#39;s simplest form anyway. Try it out for yourself over on the <a href="/search">search page</a> and let me know what you think.</p>

<p>If you are interested in exactly how I&#39;ve gone about this, you&#39;re in luck. It&#39;s definitely not perfect yet, but, regardless, I have released the code <a href="https://github.com/mathaywarduk/jekyll-search">on GitHub</a> so other Jekyll users can use it, alter it, even improve on it.</p>

<p>There are a few things things I&#39;d like to fix/tidy up in the future, like:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The JSON feed isn&#39;t very &#39;pretty&#39; - I know this isn&#39;t important, but I&#39;m all for well-formed markup.</p></li>
<li><p>Date formatting would be nice. - I&#39;ve done this on this site myself by tweaking the Javascript file, but it&#39;s not ideal to force people to use my date formatting, so it&#39;s not in the repo. </p></li>
<li><p>Make the script into a jQuery plugin - This would make it possible to customise your search function without having to change the plugin itself.</p></li>
</ul>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/jekyll-search">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/jekyll-search" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2014-02-26T17:33:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>Modular CSS with Sass &amp; BEM</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/blog/write-modular-css-with-sass-and-bem.jpg" alt="Modular CSS with Sass &amp; BEM" />
                    <p>I wrote a feature for <a href="http://netmagazine.com">Net magazine</a>&rsquo;s December issue about creating a living modular framework.</p>

<figure class="media">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/write-modular-css-with-sass-and-bem.jpg" alt="Net Magazine" class="media__item">
</figure>

<p>Here it is.</p>

<hr>

<p>While there are already many frontend frameworks available for free, it&rsquo;s often preferable to write the code yourself. In this tutorial, we will explore how to use the <a href="http://www.sass-lang.com">Sass</a> CSS preprocessor and the <a href="http://bem.info/">BEM</a> methodology to write a ‘living framework&rsquo; that can be adapted to suit any development project.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Sass enables us to write CSS in small, easy-to-navigate modules.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Meaning we can start with base styles and bolt on any components we might need for the system we&rsquo;re currently building.</p>

<p>We can also make our code easier to understand using well-constructed comments and clear naming conventions for our classes and variables. The BEM methodology gives us this clarity. BEM stands for Block-Element-Modifier and is designed to help modularise frontend development by breaking everything into blocks containing elements, then using modifiers to tweak them.</p>

<p>To apply the BEM methodology, we give each element within a block a class. Consider an unordered list:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ul class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Item 1&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Item 2&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item list__item--end&quot;&gt;Item 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</code></pre>

<p>The unordered list has the block class list while each list item has the element class <strong>list__item</strong>. Only the final list item has the additional modifier class <strong>list__item—end</strong>. Each class follows the BEM syntax:</p>

<pre><code>.BLOCK{__ELEMENT[--MODIFIER]}</code></pre>

<h2>Get Started</h2>

<p>Set up the project by creating two directories: <strong>assets</strong> and <strong>static</strong>. The static directory will contain the compiled CSS and everything else that must be deployed, while the assets folder will contain any resources that don&rsquo;t need to be deployed (in this instance, our Sass files).</p>

<p>With Sass installed on an environment, it&rsquo;s necessary to ask it to <strong>watch</strong> for changes in the SCSS files and update the static CSS files accordingly. This is a pretty simple one-liner in a Terminal window:</p>

<pre><code>sass --watch assets/sass:static/css</code></pre>

<p>Sass should have created a <strong>screen.css</strong> file in our <strong>/static/css/</strong> directory. Although at this point the file is empty, we will link to it from our HTML. (The <strong>assets/sass</strong> directory must exist for this to work).</p>

<p>Although we want our modules to be independent, there are always variables, functions and mixins that are used by multiple modules: for example, a mixin for outputting rems with a pixel fallback, or site-wide colour variables. With this in mind, we need to create <strong>_base.scss</strong> in our <strong>/assets/sass</strong> directory and include them there.</p>

<p>Using BEM as a basis for variable names will reduce the number of variables used and help other developers who might pick up the framework later on. By following this convention, we can add variables for colour and text size to our <strong>_base.scss</strong> file. For example:</p>

<pre><code>$color__primary--light: #DD0000 !default;
$color__primary: #C10000 !default;
$color__primary--dark: #990000 !default;

$base__font-size: 15 !default;
$base__line: 20 !default;</code></pre>

<p>And a simple function for calculating em sizes:</p>

<pre><code>@function calc-em($target, $context: $base__font-size) {
    @return ($target / $context) * 1em;
}</code></pre>

<p>Next, create <strong>_config.scss</strong>, which will later be used to override the default module variables, and <strong>screen.scss</strong>, the master Sass file. This will import the modules to be compiled into CSS for use on your website. Start by simply importing the <strong>base</strong> and <strong>config</strong> modules:</p>

<pre><code>@import &quot;base&quot;;
@import &quot;config&quot;;</code></pre>

<p>Rather than asking Sass to create multiple CSS files and linking each one into our HTML document, use the Sass <strong>@import</strong> directive to combine all the modules into one master CSS file. This reduces the amount of HTTP requests required, thereby improving performance.</p>

<h2>Adding modules</h2>

<p>Create a directory in <strong>/assets/sass</strong> called <strong>modules</strong>. This will house all the additional modules you add to your site for styling different forms of content. First off, add a CSS reset module (<strong>_reset.scss</strong>). Paste in the reset code of your choice and import it into the master file in the same way as before.</p>

<p>When you save the changes to the master file, notice that your Terminal process has detected changes and overwritten the <strong>screen.css</strong> file used by your web page. Opening the file, you can see the contents of the reset have been ported across.</p>

<p>At this point, you can begin to see the workflow in action. Being able to import snippets of code into a master file means we can easily toggle individual modules on or off as needed.</p>

<p>We can create a module called <strong>_text.scss</strong> and then start adding base styles for headers, paragraphs, and so on:</p>

<pre><code>h1 {
    font-size: calc-em(36);
    line-height: (40/36);
    font-family: &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
    margin-bottom: calc-em(10, 40);
    font-weight: bold;
    color: $color__primary;
}

h2 {
    font-size: calc-em(24);
    line-height: (28/24);
    font-family: "Helvetica Neue", Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
    margin-bottom: calc-em(15, 40);
    color: $color__primary;
}

h3 {
    font-size: calc-em(20);
    line-height: (22/20);
    font-family: "Helvetica Neue", Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
    margin-bottom: calc-em(15, 40);
}

p {
    font-size: calc-em(15);
    line-height: (20/15);
    font-family: &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
    margin-bottom: calc-em(10, 15);
}</code></pre>

<p>As there is quite a lot of repeated CSS here, we can abstract this out into variables and a mixin for text styling, reducing the amount of code used and making any future tweaks quicker.</p>

<pre><code>$text__family-sans:  &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif !default;

$text__size--alpha: 36 !default;
$text__size--beta: 30 !default;
$text__size--gamma: 24 !default;
$text__size--delta: 15 !default;

$text__line--alpha: 40 !default;
$text__line--beta: 36 !default;
$text__line--gamma: 30 !default;
$text__line--delta: 20 !default;

$text__colour--base: #333333 !default;
$text__colour--alpha: #990000 !default;
$text__colour--beta: #990000 !default;
$text__colour--gamma: #333333 !default;
$text__colour--delta: #333333 !default;

@mixin text($size, $line, $margin: 0, $family: $text__family-sans) {
    font-size: calc-em($size);
    line-height: ($line/$size);
    font-family: $family;
    margin-bottom: calc-em($margin, $size);
}

html {
    font-size: $base__font-size * 1px;
}

body {
    @include text($base__font-size, $base__line);
}

h1 {
    @include text($text__size--delta, $text__line--delta, 15);
    font-weight: bold;
    color: $color__primary;
}

h2 {
    @include text($text__size--beta, $text__line--beta, 15);
    color: $text__colour--beta;
}

h3 {
    @include text($text__size--gamma, $text__line--gamma, 15);
    color: $text__colour--gamma;
}

p {
    @include text($text__size--delta, $text__line--delta, 10);
    color: $text__colour--delta;
}</code></pre>

<p>The approach we&rsquo;re using for naming colour variables may not be practical when trying to remember which colours are used in context to a design. To counteract this we have used module variables with more contextual names. Each variable is given a <strong>!default</strong> flag, which allows us to override them in our <strong>_config.scss</strong> file if we prefer:</p>

<pre><code>$text__family-sans: &quot;Proxima Nova&quot;, &quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;, Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
$text__size--beta: 30;
$text__line--beta: 36;

$text__colour--base: $color__neutral--dark;
$text__colour--alpha: $color__primary;
$text__colour--beta: $color__primary;
$text__colour--gamma: $text__colour--base;
$text__colour--delta: $text__colour--base;</code></pre>

<p>You may ask what the point of declaring then overriding these variables is, and, for one-off use, there isn&rsquo;t one. But what we have now is the beginnings of a modular framework that we can use as a basis for any frontend project, adding and importing more modules as we add more elements to our system.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Redeclaring variables simply reduces the need for dependency between modules.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And gives us a cleaner starting point for each new project.</p>

<h2>Making code easier to understand</h2>

<p>You could be forgiven for thinking that any developer could now pick up your work and understand italmost instantly, but that&rsquo;s not always the case. Fortunately, there are ways to make your code even easier to understand. Firstly, Sass comments are not compiled, so will not add any weight to our compiled CSS file, so we can write as much as we like to be extra helpful. For instance, I always like to add comment blocks to mixins and functions.</p>

<p>Secondly, we can use the BEM methodology. For example, we could create a Sass module for lists where inheritance is obvious:</p>

<pre><code>.list {
    padding-left: calc-em(10);
}

.list__item {
    margin-bottom: calc-em(10);
}

.list__item--end {
    margin-bottom: 0;
}</code></pre>

<p>To add more bullets to this list, we could then create a modifier and include that class on the unordered list element:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ul class="list list--bullet"&gt;
    &lt;li class="list__item"&gt;Bulleted list item 1&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class="list__item"&gt;Bulleted list item 2&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class="list__item list__item--end"&gt;Bulleted list item 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</code></pre>

<pre><code>.list--bullet {
    list-style-type: disc;
    padding-left: calc-em(25);
}</code></pre>

<h2>Putting it all together</h2>

<p>Using the styles we have created, let&rsquo;s put together a very simple page based on one of my favourite subjects - the quiff:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;article class=&quot;layout__container&quot;&gt;
&lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Hair styling for beginners&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Tips and tricks on creating a masterful quiff.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting your hair to stand up, and stay up during a busy day in the office can be a bit of a hassle at times. But here&amp;rsquo;s a full-proof method to achieving follicular greatness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;media media--full&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;media__item&quot; src=&quot;http://static.fashionbeans.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/quiffmain1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;media__caption&quot;&gt;Young Elvis had a magnificent quiff.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;list list--bullet&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Hair dryer&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Styling putty&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Finishing spray&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Method&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;list list--number list--method&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Wash and condition your hair as normal.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Towel dry you hair until it is only slightly damp.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Rub a small amount of styling putty between the tips of your fingers and style your quiff.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Blow dry into shape, using a brush to pull your hair up.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li class=&quot;list__item&quot;&gt;Add shine and extra hold by applying some finishing spray.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;</code></pre>

<p>Our HTML page needs a bit of styling, so we can go ahead and create additional modules for layout and media,
while including additional styles for the number and method list modifiers.</p>

<p>The following code example shows how the modifiers in <strong>_lists.scss</strong> may look, with module-specific variables being included at the top.
For example:</p>

<pre><code>$list__number-color: #CC0000 !default;

.list--number {
    counter-reset: items;
    padding-top: calc-em(5);

    .list__item {
        margin-bottom calc-em(5);

        &amp;:before {
            counter-increment: items 1;
            content: counter(items, decimal) &quot;.&quot;;
            color: $list__number-color;
            margin-right: calc-em(5);
        }
    }

    .list__item--end {
        margin-bottom: 0;
    }
}

.list--method {
    @extend .list--number;

    .list__item {
        margin-bottom: calc-em(15);

        &amp;:before {
            @include text($text__size--beta, $text__line--beta);
            font-style: italic;
        }
    }

    .list__item--end {
        margin-bottom: 0;
    }
}</code></pre>

<p>There are examples of a layout and a media module in the <a href="https://github.com/mathaywarduk/simple-sass-framework">Github repository</a> that accompanies this tutorial, but I&rsquo;ll let you be creative here and decide for yourself how to build them.</p>

<figure class="media">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/BEM_Sass_3.png" alt="Module files" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Self-contained module files set out base styles for content types. They&rsquo;re used only when needed</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2>Converting to ems</h2>

<p>In this framework we&rsquo;ve been using em sizing units throughout, which on smaller scale projects isn&rsquo;t a problem. But issues surrounding compounding font-sizes can crop up when we nest HTML elements. To combat this, we can use rem (root em) units. To do this, we&rsquo;d set a base font size on our HTML element. We already have a variable for this. For example:</p>

<pre><code>html {
    font-size: $base-font-size;
}</code></pre>

<p>Then we would write a function to calculate rems and use that in place or our original <strong>calc-em()</strong> function:</p>

<pre><code>@function calc-rem($target) {
    @return ($target / $base_font-size) * 1 rem;
}</code></pre>

<p>Rems are supported in later versions of <a href="caniuse.com/rem">all major browsers</a>, but for legacy support, we can use a pixel fallback.</p>

<h2>Going further</h2>

<p>This is a very simple example, but the potential of a Sass and BEM-based framework is enormous.</p>

<p>Using the workflow outlined in this tutorial, you can create an essential building block that you can make use of for all your future projects, no matter how large they are, simply by adding modules as necessary.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s important to remember that while you are building one system, you should make the base module as simple, and therefore reusable, as possible. Specificity can then be added using the <strong>_config.scss</strong> file and BEM modifiers.</p>

<hr />

<p>This article originally appeared in issue 249 of <a href="http://www.netmagazine.com">Net Magazine</a>.</p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/modular-css-with-sass-and-bem">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/modular-css-with-sass-and-bem" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2014-01-17T09:45:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>What's in a name?</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/name.jpg" alt="What's in a name?" />
                    <p>This is a real discussion (with most of the swearing removed) within the Erskine front-end team about CSS naming conventions for a button. Hopefully it illustrates our attention to detail and how much we care about getting things right... or at least our stubborn and argumentative side.</p>

<p><strong>Mat:</strong> <em>&ldquo;What should I call this button?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>Robin:</strong> <em>&ldquo;What?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Well it&rsquo;s a button, so has the class .button, but it&rsquo;s also the primary call to action, that&rsquo;s why it&rsquo;s red.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>R:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Oh, .button—red?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Hmmm, I was thinking .button—primary&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>R:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Yeah, but then how does another developer know which one is &lsquo;primary&rsquo;?&rdquo;</em> (Robin is obsessed with the <a href="http://erskinedesign.com/blog/front-end-maintenance-and-ladder-abstraction/">ease of maintenance</a>).</p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;But what if we change the button colour later on?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>R:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Find and replace!&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>Tom:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Noooo!&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;???&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;I know what Robin thinks and he is wrong, use .button--primary; if we start doing .button--red, I quit!&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;I don&#39;t like it either, but .button--primary has issues too. I suppose for colours it works, but what about size?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;.button--primary .button--alpha; .button--red is basically the same as .font-size-12px&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;That&#39;s cool, but what happens when I&#39;ve made .button--alpha a certain size and then someone introduces a larger button?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>R:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Yeah, ‘I want this button to be dark red&rsquo; - Phil&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>R:</strong>  <em>&ldquo;.button__primary--in-between-primary-and-secondary&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;What are the variants/axes that we typically have? Colour? Size? What else?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;errrrr... Gender?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Any how&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Primary, secondary, tertiary for colour? Alpha, beta gamma for size?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;I guess the problem with the colour thing is that there is a hierarchy in the naming that may or may not actually be present in the design.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Yeah so we need a non-linear naming convention... We could name them after famous dogs!&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;The problem is we also need to make them understandable.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;.button--lassie? .button—laika?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;The problem is we also need to make them understandable.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>R:</strong> <em>&ldquo;.button--red makes sense, just admit it.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;.button--red is evil and leads to the road to hell.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;How about this for an example: at different breakpoints an area consistently has different background colours, sometimes red, sometimes white, so a .button--red in that area can&#39;t actually be red all the time...&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>R:</strong> <em>&ldquo;That&rsquo;s a good point.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;So all of a sudden you have CSS like:&rdquo;</em></p>

<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="text language-text" data-lang="text">.button--red {
   background-color: white;
}
</code></pre></div>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;And I go insane and kill everyone&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;So what&#39;s the conclusion? Other than Robin is dumbs.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>R:</strong> <em>&ldquo;.button--color-red-to-white. Done. Ship it. Open-source that mother.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;£$%^&amp;!&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;So... Colours: primary, secondary, tertiary... Sizes: alpha, beta, gamma, delta...&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Just say yes!&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>T:</strong> <em>&ldquo;With sizes is our mistake to start at one end of the range? By defining alpha too early etc.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;Yeah but if we assume that&rsquo;s going to happen, we can prepare for it. Sorted.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>R:</strong> <em>&ldquo;I still don&rsquo;t agree...&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;(eyeroll)&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><strong>M:</strong> <em>&ldquo;So, Tom, any thoughts on a name for your pending new arrival...?&rdquo;</em></p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/whats-in-a-name">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/whats-in-a-name" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2014-01-07T11:30:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>Getting started</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/getting-started.jpg" alt="Getting started" />
                    <p>Being approached by a couple of enthusiastic students and asked <em>&ldquo;how do we get a job in the industry?&rdquo;</em> was a surprisingly awkward experience. I had no idea at first. I just told them how I got into it and then the ideas starting spouting out, from myself, from other members of the Erskine team, and other industry professionals who were around at the time.</p>

<p>All of them were different. That&rsquo;s our industry, there&rsquo;s no set path into it. Some will have been to university, some will be &lsquo;self-taught&rsquo; and some will have progressed from an internship.</p>

<p>The problem is that the digital industry changes so quickly. The details of how I got started might not be relevant today, 8 years on, but the basic concepts still are.</p>

<h2>Build a portfolio</h2>

<p>The first thing I&rsquo;d suggest to any budding developer or designer is to put together a portfolio. Online. That&rsquo;s the medium you want to be working with, so it&rsquo;s only common sense that you use it.</p>

<p>When a potential employer is looking through CVs and portfolios the fact that you might have done some work for a big brand like Nike or the BBC definitely stands out. But the likelihood is that you haven&rsquo;t, so you need to stand out in other ways. Real enthusiasm can beat qualifications and experience.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Start by not doing the same as everyone else. No redesigns of Twitter, Facebook or whatever.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Do some real work if you can, for friends or family, they might even agree to throw you some cash for it, but remember that, at this point, it&rsquo;s not about the money. Go all out and produce something you&rsquo;re proud of, it&rsquo;ll pay off later.</p>

<p>And if you can&rsquo;t find jobs to do, make some up. Build a site for a fictional company, redesign a website that actually needs it, build up that portfolio until you&rsquo;re proud of it.</p>

<h2>Mingle</h2>

<p>The old phrase, <em>&ldquo;it&rsquo;s not what you know, but who you know&rdquo;</em>, is at least part accurate, so get to know people who are already working in the industry. Follow them on Twitter by all means, but meeting them face-to-face is always better.</p>

<p>Attend some industry events. Starting small. There&rsquo;s no point forking out £150 for a conference ticket if you get scared and don&rsquo;t talk to anyone. Most cities will have a local meet-up, whether it&rsquo;s just a few drinks in a bar or a bunch of talks in a community centre, and this is where you&rsquo;re likely to meet your future employer, or future colleagues.</p>

<h2>Read and write</h2>

<p>Whether it&rsquo;s your own blog or the rationale for your portfolio, write about the work you&rsquo;re doing, what challenges you&rsquo;ve faced and how you&rsquo;ve overcome these. Nobody&rsquo;s perfect, your future employer knows that. Showing your ability to learn and your understanding of the challenges involved is far more impressive than some polished work which was apparently easy to do.</p>

<p>While you&rsquo;re at it, read other people&rsquo;s blogs. People who are doing the job you want. This is free knowledge, soak it up. Go to the library and read books, new ones and, especially if you&rsquo;re looking to be a designer, old ones.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t be lazy</h2>

<p>Ok, so you have a portfolio that you&rsquo;re proud of and you&rsquo;re going to send it out to a few agencies you&rsquo;d like to work at, what do you say? This is tough.</p>

<p>Doing your research will make this easier. Find out about the company and what they do. There must be a reason why you&rsquo;ve chosen to apply there after all. Write to a specific person. If you don&rsquo;t know who, call the office and ask.</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve told them why you&rsquo;re interested in working for them, you&rsquo;re all but done. Finish off by saying where you&rsquo;d like your career to go in the near future, attach your CV and link to your portfolio, and say thank you.</p>

<p>Try to keep the whole thing quite short, agency life can be busy, so long emails will often get ignored, or forgotten.</p>

<h2>Ask about an internship</h2>

<p>A lot of agencies will take on interns, not a lot of them advertise the fact. Ask. That&rsquo;s what Robin did, and now he&rsquo;s a vital member of the Erskine team.</p>

<p>Robin was a paid intern. Unpaid internships can be demoralising and I&rsquo;d only ever suggest them if you were living with your parents or already had lots of money in the bank. If you go for it, make sure you get paid in different ways. Soak up as much knowledge as you can and keep constant notes. They&rsquo;ll help you remember things and write your CV for when you want to apply for a paid job.</p>

<h2>Check the details</h2>

<p>If you received an application that was riddled with errors, you&rsquo;d assume a low quality of work in their portfolio. You&rsquo;d be more attune to errors that you&rsquo;d usually overlook.</p>

<p>Check everything you send out, from the CV to the portfolio itself. Have someone you trust check it too (there&rsquo;s a reason we never check our own work) and be open to suggestions.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Only when you are 100% happy with what you&rsquo;re sending should you send it.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2>Good luck</h2>

<p>Other things to remember would be:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Always be humble – don&rsquo;t pretend you&rsquo;re the best designer the world has ever seen. You&rsquo;re not. At least not yet.</p></li>
<li><p>Be professional – as an example, don&rsquo;t tell the company who&rsquo;ve offered you an internship that you&rsquo;re waiting on an answer from one of their competitors. Their offer will be withdrawn. Quickly.</p></li>
<li><p>Avoid buzzwords – It&rsquo;s fine to use terms like Responsive Web Design, because it&rsquo;s an actual valid approach to design. But you&rsquo;re not a web curator or a thought leader. A quick and easy rule: If it sounds like bullshit, it is bullshit.</p></li>
</ul>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/getting-started">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/getting-started" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2013-11-18T17:36:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>Playing the wrong tune</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/tune.png" alt="Playing the wrong tune" />
                    <p>Music is an important part of advertising. It can evoke feelings which influence a consumers mood and even trigger memories of products when particular tracks are heard elsewhere. If done right.</p>

<p>To get it right, advertising agencies will spend a long time considering the entire concept of the advert, from a storyboard to the music and calls to action. They know what reactions the ad should have with the audience and they&rsquo;ll use every opportunity to encourage those reactions.</p>

<p>Disparate Youth is a track by Santigold that you&rsquo;ve most likely heard. It&rsquo;s been used by Direct Line on it&rsquo;s adverts since 2012. At the time the song wasn&rsquo;t that well known (it only reached number 96 in the UK charts). But as the ad is played more, the music becomes more popular, meaning you&#39;re more likely to hear the song in a bar, in the supermarket, wherever, and you&#39;ll subconsciously think of Direct Line.</p>

<div class="media__video">
    <iframe width="700" height="394" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/-N33AjS5dvs?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>

<p>That&rsquo;s not the only example of this kind of subliminal musical messaging, have a listen to <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=51V1VMkuyx0">Young Folks by Peter, Bjorn and John</a>.</p>

<p>Volkswagen&rsquo;s latest advert, Woofswagen, illustrates the diversity of it&rsquo;s range using the diversity of the breeds of dog that might be carried around within them. Nice idea. I love dogs. But the best part of the ad, for me, is the music. It&rsquo;s simple, beautiful and fun. Dogs are fun too. So Volkswagen&rsquo;s are fun, right? Let&rsquo;s buy a Volkswagen.</p>

<div class="media__video">
    <iframe width="700" height="525" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/65Rrl6Lka18?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>

<p>So that&rsquo;s the good, but now for the reason I thought about this article in the first place.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;ve seen a few adverts recently that really ground on me, like the clich&eacute;d &lsquo;nails on a blackboard&rsquo;.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>First off, Volvo&rsquo;s new ad for the V40 R-Design is lazy, in that it looks like every other car advert. Close ups of the vehicle as it drives down the road, through an interesting landscape. Make your own mind up whether this is a tried and tested technique or just the cheapest way to put something together quickly. </p>

<p>Musically, it&rsquo;s lazy too. Volvo is a Swedish brand, Little Dragon are a Swedish band. So they must go together...</p>

<div class="media__video">
    <iframe width="700" height="525" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/3iVns7YSNmk?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>

<p>I like this song, but as a layer in this advert it jars. A lot. From the drums at the beginning to the lyrics that have no association to the product. So much so that they get shouted over with the voiceover.</p>

<p>Now, the video below is the French version, as the UK version isn&rsquo;t available online, but Ariel have made a simple mistake with their choice on the 3-in-1 pods advert.</p>

<div class="media__video">
    <iframe width="700" height="525" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/a8lDmLDpfHQ?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>

<p>By choosing a song that is already largely associated with another product, the effectiveness of it is diluted. If you hear this song in the pub, you don&rsquo;t hear washing powder, you hear posh kids sleeping around in the more affluent areas of London.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m sure it&rsquo;s very hard to get this part of an advert right, but surely it&rsquo;s obvious when it&rsquo;s wrong. If more time is invested in choosing the right track, the benefits are there to be seen. As an afterthought, the ad can simply be forgotten.</p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/playing-the-wrong-tune">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/playing-the-wrong-tune" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2013-11-07T15:39:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>Is this progress?</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/progress.jpg" alt="Is this progress?" />
                    <p>This week one of my colleagues was amazed to hear that Twitter is written using pure CSS and not a preprocessor.</p>

<p>That same colleague also couldn&#39;t remember if CSS selectors were nested within media queries or vice versa. I&#39;m not surprised. And they&#39;re not alone.</p>

<p>I&#39;ve done it. The other weekend I made a quick holding page for my parent&#39;s allotment association. For the first time in months I wasn&#39;t using Sass and Compass and so I couldn&#39;t use a nice mixin for rem sizing. Instead I had to calculate the values myself using good old fashioned mathematics. Google was my saviour. As it was with text-shadow, box-shadow and border-radius.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Are these tools, that make our lives as developers easier, progressing our skills or reducing our basic skillset?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Can I still put CSS on my CV? Yeah, and of course I can. Not that I need a CV, <a href="/mark-as-spam">LinkedIn recruiters</a> have every job anyone could ever want, and they&#39;re gonna tell you about them whether you like it or not!</p>

<p>On one hand, I think preprocessors are great tools. Not only do they reduce the amount you have to write (do I really need to write all those vendor prefixes?), they also highlight any errors you might make in the process.</p>

<p>Conflictingly, the other side of the argument. The reliance on a tool that requires us to write syntax that will not be understood by any browser, puts us in a similar boat to those who were using Dreamweaver or FrontPage to drag and drop their way to a website in the early 2000s.</p>

<p>A similar boat. Not the same. While we&#39;re using methods to make things easier, we still understand the output.</p>

<p>Nobody argues that to build websites we should understand exactly how the internet works, or the ins and outs of a browser&#39;s rendering engine. Likewise we don&#39;t ask software developers to fully understand how there code is understood by an operating system. And the makers of an OS don&#39;t need to write everything in binary. It&#39;s layers.</p>

<p>The real question is, does this extra layer improve our ability to build websites properly? No, but it doesn&#39;t diminish it either. It&#39;s not progression, it&#39;s a process change.</p>

<p>And I much prefer this process to the previous one.</p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/is-this-progress">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/is-this-progress" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2013-10-18T15:39:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>Mark as spam</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/spam.jpg" alt="Mark as spam" />
                    <p>The definition of spam is an unsolicited electronic message. (That and canned meat of dubious origins).</p>

<p>Based on the first example, if you try to offer me a job on LinkedIn despite my profile stating that I&#39;m not interested in hearing from recruitment salespeople, I&#39;m going to mark it as spam.</p>

<p>While I&#39;ll do this with all unsolicited crap that I get, LinkedIn is by far the &#39;spammiest&#39; platform I&#39;ve been on. And it&#39;s no accident. It&#39;s built that way on purpose.</p>

<p>LinkedIn allows people business (desperate) enough to upgrade to a Pro account the ability to find and, more importantly, message anyone. Not just the people in their network. Not just the users who have already connected with you. Everyone.</p>

<p>This makes LinkedIn popular with that lowest type of salesperson... the lazy recruitment agent.</p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/mark-as-spam">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/mark-as-spam" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2013-10-18T14:43:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>Behind the scenes</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/blog/behind-the-scenes.jpg" alt="Behind the scenes" />
                    <p>A while back I started working on a pretty nice, but simple, <a href="http://behindthescenes.tribeuk.co.uk/go">interactive HTML5 video</a>.</p>

<p>The desire was to promote the <a href="http://www.tribeuk.co.uk/portfolio">art direction</a> service offered by the company I worked for at the time, <a href="http://www.tribeuk.co.uk">Tribe</a>, via well-produced video content.</p>

<p>Although it was all but finished when I left the company a month later, it&rsquo;s taken a while to get the final tweaks done as is always the case with internal projects, especially with the attention to detail Tribe are known for.</p>

<figure class="media">
    <a href="http://behindthescenes.tribeuk.co.uk/go"><img src="/static/images/blog/behind-the-scenes.jpg" alt="Behind the scenes" class="media__item"></a>
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Behind the scenes at a Tribe photoshoot</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Now it&rsquo;s alive and kicking on the internet I&#39;m pleased to see it getting some attention over social media. <a href="http://www.chrisjpavey.co.uk">The video alone is excellently put together</a>, but the interactive element just adds that something more.</p>

<p>You can <a href="http://behindthescenes.tribeuk.co.uk/go">take a look behind the scenes</a> on the Tribe website.</p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/behind-the-scenes">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/behind-the-scenes" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2013-09-19T18:07:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>Teach me web design</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/teach.png" alt="Teach me web design" />
                    <p>As a web developer of some 10 years, there are two things I&rsquo;m regularly asked by friends and acquaintances: <em>&ldquo;Can you build me a website?&rdquo;</em> and <em>&ldquo;Can you teach me web design?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>The answer to the first question has changed a bit over the years from <em>&ldquo;Yes, for a price&rdquo;</em> to <em>&ldquo;No, but I know someone who can&rdquo;</em>. I&rsquo;ve come to value my free time more and more as I&rsquo;ve got older. The answer to the other has always been:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Sure, have you got 5 years?&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A number plucked arbitrarily from the air, but large enough to make a point; learning &lsquo;web design&rsquo; is not a quick thing.</p>

<p>Well at least it didn&rsquo;t use to be. Since around about the time I was considering whether to go to university or not, and still today, I&rsquo;ve heard post-grads complain that what they&rsquo;re taught during the 3 or 4 years that leaves them with a heap of debt, is way behind the working practices of the industry. This has always led me to believe that the best way to learn digital design or development is through experience, and that experience took me years to gain (at least to the extent that I would call myself a good developer).</p>

<p>More recently however, we&rsquo;ve seen services like <a href="http://teamtreehouse.com/">Treehouse</a> and <a href="https://www.steer.me/">Steer</a> aim to teach people with little or no experience the skills to become employees in the digital industry, with the later claiming to teach HTML, CSS and Javascript in just 5 days.</p>

<p>This has got me thinking recently;</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Q. Could I teach someone all this in 5 days? A. Most probably, but with a few caveats.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>First of all, I could only teach <a href="http://www.w3.org/html/wg/drafts/html/master/">HTML</a> and <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS/">CSS</a> to the latest W3C draft (and so I should) but unfortunately it would take an age to go through every little browser quirk and the preferred solution (if there is one).</p>

<p>Secondly, Javascript is a much bigger fish than people give credit for and it has many uses. Within the 5 days it would most likely only be possible to touch the basics of DOM interaction, animation and AJAX. I wouldn&rsquo;t call this &lsquo;learning Javascript&rsquo;, it&rsquo;s more &lsquo;learning to use Javascript to enhance website interactions&rsquo; - but that&rsquo;s a bit of a mouthful.</p>

<p>And I can only teach the way I work. This is important. In a small case where I might show someone the ropes, the fact that those ropes are Mat Hayward&trade; branded makes no difference to the industry; just another average developer to add to the pool. However, if someone (or someones) is teaching a whole bunch of people at once, churning out &lsquo;job-ready&rsquo; graduates and they&rsquo;ve all learnt to code in the same way, then what differentiates them from each other when they apply for those jobs? Nothing. So how can an employer make that choice? Personally, I&rsquo;d go to the person with some experience.</p>

<p>I think it&rsquo;s important to realise, if you&rsquo;re thinking of taking one (or more) of these courses that, although you&rsquo;ll no doubt learn a lot and will definitely be able to build a website when you&rsquo;ve finished, you should never be done learning. In this industry, that I love and hate in equal measures things change very quickly, and before you know it you&rsquo;re looking over your shoulder at the <a href="http://www.robinrendle.com">young, up-and-coming kids</a> that make you question how much your experience actually counts for.</p>

<p>And while you can be reassured that it does count for a lot, it&rsquo;s important to note that relying solely on that experience will soon enough count for nothing.</p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/teach-me-web-design">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/teach-me-web-design" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2013-08-29T16:34:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>A rant about SEO</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/seo.jpg" alt="A rant about SEO" />
                    <p>SEO shouldn&rsquo;t exist. In a perfect world, there would be no place for Brian the Search Engine Optimisation Consultant* or any of his&nbsp;cronies.</p>

<p>Every client includes it on a brief, &lsquo;first page ranking&rsquo;, &lsquo;top of Google&rsquo;. That&rsquo;s easy. Almost every page on every site on the internet is top of Google, <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=mat+hayward+nottingham">if the search term is specific enough</a>. But that&rsquo;s not what they want. What they really want is conversions.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Search engines present users with the most relevant pages based on the search terms they enter.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The SEO <em>wizards</em> know the &lsquo;tricks-of-the-trade&rsquo; to falsify your web page&rsquo;s relevance for the keywords required, giving your page a higher ranking than it actually deserves, and they&rsquo;ll happily charge you to do it. They&rsquo;ll have you believe it&rsquo;s some kind of magical dark art, passed from generation-to-generation. It&rsquo;s not. And there are two problems with their ideals and their methods. When Google, Yahoo!, Bing and the others find out these tricks, they change their algorithms in order to nullify them. What&rsquo;s worse, users tricked into visiting the wrong page, leave. Leading to reduced conversion rates and increased bounce rates.</p>

<p>Google (et al) are in the game to make money, and they do this by serving the most relevant results to their users. Repeated users equal more advertising revenue. And what makes a search engine popular? Getting the best results first time every time. Relevance. It&rsquo;s in their interest to remove the false results.</p>

<p>To achieve a high ranking that leads to conversions, don&rsquo;t use tricks and cheats that will be out-of-date by the time your next birthday comes around. Look at the content from the users&rsquo; point of view. The best way to appear relevant is to <strong>actually be&nbsp;relevant</strong>.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>How do you convince the search engines that your page is the best result? Start by being the best result.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Employing a good web copywriter and a decent development team is a good first step on any project but it&rsquo;s also a good first step to achieving a true high ranking.</p>

<p>Web copywriters know that search engines love to ignore repetition. They will choose different keywords for each page and write original content to avoid the downfalls of repetition and to encourage in-linking (incoming links from other web pages on different domains).</p>

<p>A page with a large amount of inbound links is obviously influential. A page with inbound links from other influential pages is even more so, and the more influence a page is shown to have, the more relevance it is afforded by the major search engines.</p>

<p>If the content is good enough that it will be linked to, and linked to from influential sites, then the ranking will improve. But it&rsquo;s possible to help it along without being naughty. If a website is for a business that operates in a localised area, it&rsquo;s useful to add it to web directories to improve in-linking. The most influential of these are <a href="http://www.google.co.uk/business/placesforbusiness/">Google Places</a>, <a href="http://yell.com">Yell</a> and <a href="http://dmoz.org">Dmoz</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Good developers will always write valid, semantic code and keep page load to a minimum. Search engines like both of these things.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Firstly, semantic code often presents less code and more content, so a greater percentage of the document read by a search engine index will be keywords.</p>

<p>Secondly, while <a href="http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.co.uk/2010/04/using-site-speed-in-web-search-ranking.html">Google admits that site speed isn&rsquo;t a massive factor in search results</a>, it is still a factor and, efforts should be made to make webpages as quick to load as possible. If only for the sake of the user. At Erskine, we&rsquo;ve started to set global performance budgets on the websites we build. That is, setting a maximum page weight, http requests and response time. It allows us to concentrate on what&rsquo;s important, content and user experience, without getting carried away with huge images and obtrusive JavaScript animations.</p>

<p>After a website is pushed live, there are a lot of things that can be done to give it a head start. To prompt search engines to crawl a site, it&rsquo;s possible to submit an XML sitemap to each of them. This file outlines every page on a website, giving each a priority against the others.</p>

<p>Once submitted, a website is then monitored by <a href="http://www.google.com/webmasters/tools/">Google Webmaster Tools</a>, a neat little admin system which highlights any crawl errors and other issues, as well as giving tips, and tools, to improve listings.</p>

<p>Of course all of these things can be achieved by SEO consultants too, and there are good ones out there that will use the honest methods outlined above to do so. Unfortunately, there are also those that will happily take the shortcuts that exploit a hole in the system.</p>

<p>Any healthy relationship is based on trust, if one side is regularly faking or lying, they will eventually get ditched when the other side realises. Building an organic high ranking will keep everyone happy. The search engines won&rsquo;t ditch pages that remain relevant, a website&rsquo;s users will receive a better, faster experience and site owner&rsquo;s will achieve those conversion rates they wanted.</p>

<p>What the internet needs, is less SEO <em>sorcerers</em>, and more site owners that actually care about their content. Not just their conversions. These &lsquo;good&rsquo; sites will always do better in the long run, even if the &lsquo;evil&rsquo; site is at the &lsquo;top&rsquo; for a while, like in any blockbuster movie, the baddie will meet a horrible, fiery end. Be patient, be good and update your site regularly. If you build it (well) they will come.</p>

<p><small>* Cue huge backlash from SEO consultants named Brian.</small></p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/a-rant-about-seo">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/a-rant-about-seo" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2013-08-01T11:15:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>The responsive web</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/responsive-web.jpg" alt="The responsive web" />
                    <p>Last month Craig and I gave a talk at <a href="http://www.secondwednesday.org.uk/">Second Wednesday</a>, a monthly Nottingham-based event for creative and digital people, entitled The Responsive Web.</p>

<p>The talk, which attracted a <a href="https://twitter.com/jhuskisson/status/311926597194240000">record number of attendees</a>, looked at how websites can deliver both tailored design and content for a truly responsive experience. For anyone who couldn&rsquo;t make it, below is the script (which we roughly followed) for the talk:</p>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>Hello everyone, thanks for coming. We&rsquo;re Craig and Mat. We&rsquo;re senior developers at Tribe, one of the largest creative agencies in the Lace Market.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re going to talk today about the Responsive Web, and how we can build websites, not just for all devices but for all users too.</p>

<h2>Best viewed at 1024 x 768</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ll start with a bit of a history lesson. This is taken from Mat&rsquo;s personal portfolio back in 2002. It was common back then as the number of different screen sizes was low, and I have to admit I put something similar on a website back then.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>This website is best viewed at 1024×768 resolution using Internet Explorer 6.0 or higher.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But it&rsquo;s just not acceptable nowadays, because there are so many different screen sizes (I have seven just in my house). So we can&rsquo;t afford to be complacent and expect the user to do the work. Users want it to be easy, and they want it to be quick.</p>

<p>And it&rsquo;s not like we can aim for one or two screen sizes and that will serve the lion&rsquo;s share. There a a lot of differing screen resolutions used on the web now and with mobile usage growing fast, we have to cater for everyone.</p>

<h2>The Challenge</h2>

<p>So that&rsquo;s the challenge:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>How can we keep the user happy, whatever device they might be using?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And we thought of 3 solutions for that:</p>

<h2>1. Leave It</h2>

<p>The first solution is to just leave it. It&rsquo;s the easy way out, they&rsquo;ll be no extra development costs and the device will, to some extent, make it work. And one quite well-known brand that&rsquo;s doing this right now is Apple. The <a href="http://www.apple.com/">homepage of their website</a>, super scales down for use on mobile. And it works to an extent, but you have to use the pinch zoom to read anything smaller than the main message.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-apple.png" alt="The Apple website" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
    <figcaption class="media__caption">The apple website is not optimised for mobile in any way</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2>2. Mobile version</h2>

<p>Then the second option would be to build a separate mobile site. Two sites means we can target content to desktop and mobile users, but we have to update content twice every time we want to do it. A lot of companies that go down this route, often strip out lots of content, like <a href="http://www.nationalrail.co.uk/">National Rail</a>. Their mobile site shows live departures, train times and such, which will server 80% of its users&rsquo; needs. But if, for example, you wanted season ticket prices, you would have to use the desktop version, taking us back to option 1.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-nationalrail.png" alt="The Apple website" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
    <figcaption class="media__caption">National Rail have a separate mobile site</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2>3. Make it Responsive</h2>

<p>The last option, which is the one we&rsquo;re going to focus on is to Make it Responsive. And to explain what Responsive Design is we&rsquo;ll use our old friend Dave.</p>

<h2>Dave</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-dave.jpg" alt="What is responsive design?" class="media__item">
</figure>

<p>Here&rsquo;s Dave, he couldn&rsquo;t be with us tonight, but he&rsquo;s useful here as an analogy. We all like Dave, in whatever capacity he&rsquo;s in, whether it&rsquo;s Olympic Ambassador, unpaid Footballer or Forgetter of Clothes, but whatever he&rsquo;s wearing, or not wearing, and whatever he&rsquo;s doing, he&rsquo;s always the same Dave. His content never changes, but the way that content is displayed changes. And it&rsquo;s always displayed in the best way for the situation.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>And that&rsquo;s the basis of Responsive Design. Change your pants, but don&rsquo;t change your content!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a good example. This is <a href="http://thegreatdiscontent.com/">The Great Discontent</a> on a large desktop monitor. You can see the large hero image and headline, and the navigation and logo are relatively small at the top.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-tgd_1.png" alt="The Great Discontent" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
</figure>

<p>Then, as it gets smaller, the hero image and headline shrink, but stay full width, multiple columns change to one column and the navigation becomes more prominent when we get down to the mobile size.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-tgd_2.png" alt="The Great Discontent" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
</figure>

<p>And this is the <a href="http://www.time.com/">Time magazine</a> website. There&rsquo;s a lot of content there, a lot of different articles.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-time_1.png" alt="Time Magazine" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
</figure>

<p>But as you can see, when it gets smaller, the top stories and latest articles remain near the top. And the navigation changes from a long bar to a single button, allowing the content to be more prominent. With this site, and the previous one, it&rsquo;s worth noting that the look and feel doesn&rsquo;t change either, which for anyone in branding is very important.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-time_2.png" alt="Time Magazine" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
</figure>

<h2>How can we respond?</h2>

<h3>Layout</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with the most obvious part of Responsive Web Design, which is the layout. Essentially making content fit the width of the screen nicely, removing the need for zooming. We can achieve this by using percentages instead of hard pixels in our CSS and use media queries to add break-points where layouts can snap.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-layout.png" alt="Responsive layouts" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
</figure>

<p>And there are frameworks to get you started. Twitter Bootstrap has all sorts of features, including a 12 column responsive grid.</p>

<h3>Imagery</h3>

<p>And then we should look at imagery. By the far the biggest zapper of bandwidth, but if you&rsquo;re on the bus or the train, you don&rsquo;t want to wait for ages for your image to load. So at Tribe we came up with a solution, showing the user a lower resolution image to begin with, so they think the page has loaded, and then loading the higher resolution image in the background on non-mobile devices and replacing it when done.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-5.png" alt="Our responsive image solution" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
    <figcaption class="media__caption">The image on the left is 89KB, while the image on the right is only 8KB</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3>Navigation</h3>

<p>Navigation is really important too. If it&rsquo;s difficult to use, users will get annoyed and give up, so think about every iteration of the main nav. Here&rsquo;s the menu for the WWF in various stages.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-wwf.png" alt="WWF navigation" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
</figure>

<p>At the top the navigation is wide, with space to breath. As the screen gets narrower it bunches together until it disappears almost completely on the mobile version.</p>

<p>Donate and Adopt links are still very prominent, as they are the WWFs most important links, but the menu itself is hidden behind a menu icon in the top corner. Pressing that gets you all the same options as in the desktop site, because it&rsquo;s the same content.</p>

<p>And remember that as your site layout gets narrower, it&rsquo;s bound to get longer, which can be a bit of a strain on the user&rsquo;s thumb or finger. To make it easier, we can add links into sections of the content, allowing us to skip directly to comments, or jump back to the top.</p>

<h3>Content is King</h3>

<p>Always remember that the content is still the most important element of any website. Content is Still King. If you&rsquo;re users can find the content they want quickly and easily, they&rsquo;ll be happy. And they&rsquo;ll come back.</p>

<h2>The Next Level</h2>

<p>So that covers a lot of what&rsquo;s involved in Making it Responsive. Think about layout, bandwidth and images, easy navigation and most of all content, but what else can we do to be truly Responsive?</p>

<p>At Tribe, when we talk about the Responsive Web, it&rsquo;s not just about these things, it&rsquo;s also about the user experience and using different triggers like location and age to order content, not just screen size.</p>

<p>So let&rsquo;s look at the things we know about our users, how we can use them to tailor content, how some websites are already doing this and how some have been doing this for years.</p>

<h3>Location</h3>

<p>Starting with location. We can quite easily work out the users exact location, using Geolocation. And providing they allow it, we can then give them automatic driving directions to our office. Here&rsquo;s the automated map from the new Tribe site (currently in production), showing driving directions from Antenna to the Tribe office. You&rsquo;d be pretty lazy to drive, but you get the idea.</p>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-map.jpg" alt="WWF navigation" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
</figure>

<p>If we know the user is in Nottingham, and our site sells replica football shirts, we&rsquo;re unlikely to put Derby County shirts on the homepage we serve to them.</p>

<p>And as we already know the users location, we can use this to work out what the weather is like for them. We can then use this to decide which content to push to them. We&rsquo;ll have a much higher conversion rate if we push our summer holidays to user&rsquo;s in Manchester, when it&rsquo;s chucking it down outside.</p>

<p><a href="http://weatherfit.co.uk/">WeatherFit</a> is an addon for Google Adwords, meaning we can take this concept off our website, and into Google search, showing our ads only if the weather&rsquo;s right. It&rsquo;s an expensive option, but if it works, it may be a viable one.</p>

<h3>Face Recognition</h3>

<p>Face recognition is already something Xbox Live uses to log you in and Smart TVs are using it to recognise who&rsquo;s watching and serve them the right content. So it might be something we could use online. We wouldn&rsquo;t use it for internet banking or anything, but it&rsquo;s a thought.</p>

<p>One good example we saw recently was <a href="http://webdesign.maratz.com/lab/responsivetypography/realtime/">a site that recognised how far your face was from the screen</a>, and changed the size of the text to suit.</p>

<h3>Time of Day</h3>

<p>If we know the time of day or week, and we do. We can offer content based on that. For instance, a restaurant could give higher importance to its breakfast menu in the morning, then switch to lunch and dinner accordingly. Or a bar could push it&rsquo;s cocktail menu on a Friday afternoon when Pam&rsquo;s looking at what she&rsquo;s doing that weekend.</p>

<p>And if we&rsquo;re using time sensitive content on a more global scale, we could always use geolocation to compensate for timezones.</p>

<h3>Returning Visitors</h3>

<p>We&rsquo;re sure most of you have done some form of shopping online before. And so you&rsquo;re probably used to seeing recently viewed items on ASOS, Size? or Amazon. But why shouldn&rsquo;t we use that concept on non-shopping websites. We can show recently viewed articles or portfolio pieces, and taking another idea form shopping sites, we could say, you might also like this.</p>

<p>And so many websites have a welcome message on their homepage. But if I&rsquo;ve visited it before, I&rsquo;ve either already read it, or I wasn&rsquo;t interested. So why not tweak that message slightly?</p>

<h3>Login with Facebook</h3>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-web-facebook.png" alt="WWF navigation" class="media__item media__item--noshadow" />
</figure>

<p>This is the holy grail of information on our users. If we have a site that allows users to login, we can make it easier for them to sign up by adding a Connect with Facebook feature. It&rsquo;s a bit of work for us as developers, but the benefit is huge. We can know everything about them&hellip; age, gender, relationship status, hobbies, favourite films and music.</p>

<p>What if we logged into Ticketmaster and it told us <em>&ldquo;We know you like Arcade Fire and they&rsquo;re playing at the Ice Arena next Wednesday, your calendar says you&rsquo;re free.&rdquo;</em></p>

<h2>Finally</h2>

<p>The more we know about the user, the more we can structure the content to suit them. And while Responsive Web Design is a great idea, being responsive can be so much more than that. Hopefully this has given some insight into the thinking behind building a truly responsive website, on all levels.</p>

<p>And remember that:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Devices don&rsquo;t use websites, people do.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/the-responsive-web">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/the-responsive-web" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2013-02-16T14:42:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>Responsive email newsletters</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/blog/responsive-email-size.jpg" alt="Responsive email newsletters" />
                    <p>While responsive web design has taken off over the last year or so, responsive email design has been somewhat left behind. But, if you want your email to be read, surely it needs to be readable.</p>

<p>There are some brands that have already realised the benefit of making life easier for their customers. Here are 10 examples to inspire your own efforts...</p>

<h2>01. MailChimp</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-mailchimp.jpg" alt="Mailchimp newsletter" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Mailchimp have made their email newsletters ultra-easy to read</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As you&#39;d expect from an email marketing service that sends over 4billion emails a month, <a href="http://www.mailchimp.com/">Mailchimp</a>&#39;s emails are just as readable on the way to work as they are sat at your desk. The cleverest part of this email is its simplicity. The design barely changes between devices, with only the social links altering their layout for smaller screens.</p>

<h2>02. Toms</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-toms.jpg" alt="Toms newsletter" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Shoe store Toms has removed the header and footer from its newsletters</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Shoe store <a href="http://www.toms.com/">Toms</a>&#39; approach to mobile email design is to remove the header and footer sections, ensuring the primary message is visible instantly. It also uploads different images on mobile, presumably smaller in filesize for a quicker load time, but also with larger calls to action and shortened copy for a speedier conversion.</p>

<h2>03. Smashing Magazine</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-smashingmag.jpg" alt="Smashing Magazine's newsletter" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Smashing Magazine has centred its newsletter around the text</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Web design blog <a href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com/">Smashing Magazine</a>&#39;s newsletter features a simple, text-heavy design, with just one full-width image for each article. This saves time building in mobile-responsiveness because the layout scales down automatically and is still readable and fully useable without the need for zooming in.</p>

<h2>04. Moo.com</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-moo.jpg" alt="Moo's newsletter" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Moo's newsletter adapts well to smaller screen sizes</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The MOOsLetter provides readers with special offers, tips and creative ideas relating to <a href="http://www.moo.com/">Moo</a>&#39;s printing services. On a smartphone, the secondary articles within the email change from a double to single-column layout, allowing the text-size to enlarge, and all calls to action are stretched to fill the width of the screen.</p>

<h2>05. Twitter</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-twitter.jpg" alt="Twitters's newsletter" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Twitter has increased the space between elements of its newsletter to make it easier to navigate by thumb</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><a href="http://www.twitter.com/">Twitter</a>&#39;s responsive email has won lots of praise throughout the industry, and rightly so. Simplifying the header, increasing the space between reply, retweet and favourite actions and enlarging the final call to action makes this email much easier to navigate with your thumb. But why did they move the position of the Twitter flag? Form or function?</p>

<h2>06. Gilt</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-gilt.jpg" alt="Gilt's newsletter" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Designer label store Gilt wants users to move quickly through to purchase</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><a href="http://www.gilt.com/">Gilt</a> runs time-limited sales on designer labels at huge discounts and to do this it needs its users to be able to move quickly through the process from receiving an email to making a purchase. Removing the list of links on the left-hand side and reducing the size of the main navigation for smaller screens means the recipient can quickly find what might interest them and join in the sale.</p>

<h2>07. Rdio</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-rdio.jpg" alt="Rdio's newsletter" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Rdio's emails are fluid with a minimum width</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><a href="http://www.rdio.com/">Rdio</a> emails don&#39;t follow the usual design convention of a fixed 600px width. Instead their emails are fluid with a minimum width, so when viewed on a mobile, the content shown in columns simply shows in narrower columns. Usually this wouldn&#39;t work very well, but with the amount of content being small, the layout still remains intact and readable.</p>

<h2>08. Size?</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-size.jpg" alt="Size?'s newsletter" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Clothing store Size?'s email newsletter stretches the buttons to fit the width of the screen</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Emails from question mark-toting clothing store <a href="http://www.size.co.uk/">Size?</a> already look simple enough for mobile use thanks to the use of large images and click-throughs. But that hasn&#39;t stopped the company from investing some time making the mobile experience that little bit better. The number of links at the top and the bottom of the email are reduced, showing only the most important ones, and any buttons are stretched to fill the width of the email, making them easier to press.</p>

<h2>09. Mr Porter</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-mrporter.jpg" alt="Mr Porter's newsletter" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Isolated images and short and sweet descriptions make navigation easy</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This email from clothes shopping site <a href="http://www.mrporter.com/">Mr Porter</a> does not appear to be responsive or optimised for mobile, but because of its design that&#39;s not necessarily a problem. Large hero images and buttons in the top section are pretty standard for most email designs, but 28 items of clothing or accessories after that would usually be a bit much for a tiny smartphone screen. Not here. Mr Porter add short and sweet descriptions to isolated images which are perfect for fingertip pressing.</p>

<h2>10. Tribe Latest</h2>

<figure class="media media--full">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/responsive-email-tribe.jpg" alt="Tribe Latest" class="media__item">
    <figcaption class="media__caption">Tribe's newsletter has large links for easy pressing</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This might seem like a shameless plug for my own agency, <a href="http://www.tribeuk.co.uk/">Tribe</a>, and it probably is - but we&#39;ve also built our own responsive email, which alters from a variable two- and three-column layout on desktop machines to a single column layout, with larger text, on mobile using media queries. It&#39;s easy to read and links are large enough to press with a thumb or finger without having to zoom in.</p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/responsive-email-newsletters">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/responsive-email-newsletters" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2013-02-27T12:17:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
        
        <entry>
            <title>What's behind the mask?</title>
            <content type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <img src="http://mathayward.com/static/images/social/mask.jpg" alt="What's behind the mask?" />
                    <p>Our resident photography genius, Rob, recently launched his new website: <a href="http://www.panodrop.com/">panodrop.com</a>, showcasing his talent for Stereographic photography. By the end of the first day it had received over 6,000 hits and the logo masking was the hottest web design topic on Reddit. So with all the interest, we thought we&rsquo;d share, roughly, how we did it.</p>

<p>We started with the basic mask, a cut out of the logo placed on top of an image of pure white using CSS. Together these created the part of logo that changes.</p>

<figure class="media">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/pano_hole_step_1.jpg" alt="Step 1" class="media__item">
</figure>

<p>That was our default view. Then we inserted a hidden div between the mask and the white background, which would act as a placeholder for the dynamic background.</p>

<figure class="media">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/pano_hole_step_2.jpg" alt="Step 2" class="media__item">
</figure>

<p>Then, using Javascript, all we had to do was to change the background of the hidden div to whatever the user was hovering over and change the background position to follow the cursor.</p>

<figure class="media">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/pano_hole_step_3.jpg" alt="Step 3" class="media__item">
</figure>

<figure class="media">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/pano_hole_step_4.jpg" alt="Step 4" class="media__item">
</figure>

<p>One issue we came across was when hovering near the corners of images, the corners were visible in the logo. Not nice!</p>

<p>To fix this we used a bit of maths in the Javascript to implement a &ldquo;safe-zone&rdquo; on the image.</p>

<figure class="media">
    <img src="/static/images/blog/pano_hole_step_5.jpg" alt="Step 5" class="media__item">
</figure>

<p>Simple as that! We&rsquo;re really pleased with it and Rob is pleased with the conversation it&rsquo;s sparked online. Hopefully it will help him sell some prints&hellip;</p>

                    <a href="http://mathayward.com/whats-behind-the-mask">Read on</a>
                ]]>
            </content>
            <link href="http://mathayward.com/whats-behind-the-mask" type="text/html" rel="alternate" />
            <id>http://mathayward.com{ post.url }}</id>
            <author>
                <name>Mat Hayward</name>
            </author>
            <published>2012-05-02T11:13:00+00:00</published>
        </entry>
        
    
    </feed>